A Guide to the James Rogers McConnell Memorial Collections
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
James Rogers McConnell Memorial Collections 1915-1977
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2104
ca. 220 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection is established in honor of the memory of James Rogers McConnell.
Accession #2104 was given to the Library by Eleanor (McConnell) [Mrs. Ralph P.] Truitt of Baltimore, Maryland, on January 26, 1945.
Accession #2104-a was given to the Library by Dr. William James Kenneth Rockwell of Durham, North Carolina, through his father, Colonel Paul Ayres Rockwell of Asheville, North Carolina, on February 24, 1975.
Accession #2104-b was loaned to the Library for copying and return by Colonel Rockwell on February 24, 1975.
Accession #2104-c was given to the Library by Colonel Rockwell on August 1, 1975.
Accession #2104-d was given to the Library by Mademoiselle Marcelle Guérin de Precourt of Monte Carlo, Monaco, on September 29, 1975.
Accession #2104-e was given to the Library by Colonel Rockwell on November 19, 1976.
Accession #2104-f was given to the Library by Colonel Rockwell on June 17, 1977.
Accession #2104-g was given to the Library by the Moore County Historical Association, Inc. of Southern Pines, North Carolina, through Sherman W. Betts, president, on September 6, 1977.
Accession #2104-h was loaned to the Library for copying and return by Mrs. Helmut von Erffa of Piscataway, New Jersey, through Peter Stoudt, on July 21, 1980.
Accession #2104-i was given to the Library by Catherine D. Scott, Librarian, National Air and Space Museum, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D. C., on October 21, 1980.
Accession #2104-j was given to the Library by Mrs. Charles T. Grier of Carthage, North Carolina, through Peter Stoudt, on June 24, 1982.
Accession #2104-k was given to the Library by William James Kenneth Rockwell of Durham, North Carolina on May 20, 1997.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Rogers McConnell was born in Chicago, Illinois, on March 14, 1887, one of three children of Samuel Parsons and Sarah Rogers McConnell. The elder McConnell practiced law in Chicago from 1872-1889, and served as Judge of the Cook County Circuit Court from 1889-1894. After an interval of private practice, he moved to New York City, where he served as vice-president and counsel of the George A. Fuller Company until his retirement in 1904.
The younger McConnell grew up in Chicago and New York City. He gained a certificate from the Haverford School in Pennsylvania before entering the University of Virginia in 1907. He spent two years in the College and a year in the Law School, withdrawing from his studies in the spring of 1910. While at Virginia, Jim McConnell held memberships in Beta Theta Pi, Theta Nu Epsilon, O.W.L., T.I.L.K.A., and the German Club. He was King of the Hot Feet, Editor-in-Chief of Corks and Curls, Assistant Cheer Leader, and President of the Aero Club, which he had helped to found. His bonhomie and bagpipe-playing gave rise to fond memories among his college contemporaries.
After several years in business in New York and in Carthage, North Carolina, where he served as land and industrial agent for a small railroad, McConnell sailed from New York with a friend in January 1915, to enlist in the French service. Through the spring and summer of 1915 he drove for Section "Y" of the American Ambulance, in the thick of the fighting on the Western Front, around Pont-à-Mousson and the Bois-le- Pretre. He was cited for conspicuous bravery and awarded the Croix de Guerre. Some of his letters from the period were edited and published in the September 15, 1915 issue of The Outlook, with an introduction by former president Theodore Roosevelt, a strong advocate of preparedness.
A deepening conviction of the rightness of the French cause led McConnell to volunteer for service in French aviation. He trained at the flying school at Pau and was breveted for flight on February 6, 1916. On April 20, 1916 he joined the newly-formed American Escadrille (later redesignated the Lafayette Escadrille) at its operational base at Luxeuil-les-Bains, becoming one of the first four of the seven original Escadrille pilots to arrive. He participated in the squadron's first patrol on May 13, 1916, and in the aerial actions during the great German offensive at Verdun in June and the Allied counteroffensives in July and August. On July 1, 1916, he was promoted to sergeant, the rank which he held until his death.
A back injury received in a landing mishap in August 1916 near the squadron field at Bar-le-Duc forced McConnell's hospitalization in September. Although he rejoined the squadron at Cachy briefly in November 1916 and again at Ravenel in March 1917, his health never returned to normal. While convalescing, he busied himself with writing, and produced articles for World's Work magazine that were published in November 1916 and March 1917, and in book form as Flying for France which appeared in April 1917, shortly after his death. He also was best man for his friend, Paul Rockwell, the squadron's historian and publicist, at the latter's Paris wedding on December 4, 1916.
McConnell was killed in aerial combat with two German planes, above the Somme battlefields, near the village of Flavy-le-Martel, Aisne, on March 19, 1917. He thereby became the last American pilot of the squadron to die under French colors, before American entrance into the war in April 1917. His body was laid to rest where he fell, and was later re-interred at the Lafayette Escadrille memorial near Paris in accordance with his father's wishes. McConnell was memorialized with a plaque from the French government and a statue by Gutzon Borglum at the University of Virginia, and with an obelisk on the court square of his home town of Carthage, North Carolina.
Scope and Content
The James Rogers McConnell Memorial Collections consist of ca. 220 items, (1915-1917)1977, chiefly ca. 160 letters, 1915-1917, written by the University's famed aviator of the Lafayette Escadrille to his friend, Paul Ayres Rockwell and to Mademoiselle Marcelle Guérin, a French nurse serving at the hospital in Paris, France during World War I. The letters date from 1915, when McConnell served with the American Ambulance on the Western Front in France, through 1916, the year of the formation of the Escadrille, with McConnell as one of its original seven American pilots. They provide a vivid picture of McConnell's service in the cause of France, first as a non-combatant and then as a combatant. Included are accounts of his ambulance patrols (May-June, 1915) and nearby bombardments while serving on the Western Front, where he earned the Croix de Guerre for exceptional bravery under fire. Other events discussed are his first flight in a "Baby" Nieuport (May 20, 1916); the patrol of June 1, 1916 after which McConnell crashed during a landing attempt (June 3, 1916); his convalescence from back injuries received in a later crash (August-September 1916); and his role in Paul Rockwell's Paris wedding (November-December 1916).
There are also photographs and printed items pertaining to McConnell. There are photographs and printed information on McConnell's grave and other monuments to his memory. Items of interest include the proof copy of the authorized English translation (1919), published only in significantly altered form, of the account of the Lafayette Escadrille written by its French captain, Georges Thénault. The volume, inscribed personally by Thénault to Paul Rockwell, has been returned to the owner and placed on microfilm for the use of researchers.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - Letters from James Rogers McConnell to Marcelle Guérin
    - James R. McConnell, American Hospital of Paris, to Marcelle Guérin, [Paris], 1915 Feb 20; 6 p. on 3 l. (Box Box 1)
      [letter of infatuation; received first typhoid treatment; arrival of the wounded and sick; stories of troops being opposed by Austrian and Bavarian troops; three Germans brought in; empathy for a commandant general summoned from China to Marseilles and then sent to the northern front where his health failed, went to Val de Grace and protected by Americans at St. Joseph; two beautiful aeroplanes flew above the hospital; [ ] Fenton]
    - James R. McConnell, Neuilly-sur-Seine, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Feb 27; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [requests to meet with her and offer advice and any assistance; reveals his deep interest in her]
    - James R. McConnell, American Hospital of Paris, to Marcelle Guérin, [Paris], [1915 early Apr]; 2 p. on 1 l. (Box Box 1)
      [affectionate letter containing "a little farewell line" and commenting "that you are everything to me over here --or elsewhere for that matter"; squad to work with the French ambulances on the line; base to be between Nancy and Pont-àMousson]
    - James R. McConnell, Vittel, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Apr 19; 4 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [orders to proceed to Pont-à-Mousson, at the front; description of trip from Paris through the country, mentioning La Ferté Gaucher, grave sites of solders, villages levelled by shell fire, and their greeting in St. Dizier; fine hotels now turned into hospitals; being under military rule]
    - James R. McConnell, Mirecourt Vosges, to Marcelle Guérin, Neuilly-sur- Seine, [1915 Apr 19]; APCS (Box Box 1)
      [arrival at a point near Nancy the following day]
    - James R. McConnell, Nancy, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1915] Apr 21; APCS (Box Box 1)
      [written in French; arrived at Nancy]
    - James R. McConnell, Pont-à-Mousson, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Apr 23; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [pleased with post; being under strict military rule; damage to town by German shelling and the death of two little children playing in the street; constant shelling and firing of guns; business flourishing in town; danger and adventure of driving into town; some German prisoners at their base; conditions of their advance post; meeting French officers and soldiers; inquires of [Paul Ayres] Rockwell and his wedding]
    - James R. McConnell, [Pont-à-Mousson], to Marcelle Guérin, [Paris], [1915] Apr 27; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [worse at base at Dieulouard than at their advance point, Pont-à-Mousson; German shells killing one and wounding seventeen; exciting work during the bombardment; [Enos] Curtin; helping two elderly women spade their vineyard]
    - James R. McConnell, Pont-à-Mousson, to Marcelle Guérin, Neuilly- sur-Seine, [1915] May 4; APCS (Box Box 1)
      [seen first battle and evacuated the wounded with dispatch; work between the artillery and trenches; [Paul Ayres] Rockwell and his fiancé]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, [1915] May 5; 8 p. on 4 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [return from their advance point; evacuated after first big fight; have about one hundred and thirty German prisoners at their base and are using them to clean up the streets; description of the advance point and the conditions under which they work at night, comparing the complete darkness to the skies illuminated by shells; the horror of dying and wounded soldiers; women nurses at the hospital near their advance point; description of the town near their advance point; French officials being pleased with the squad; comfortable and happy except for her absence]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 May 16; 16 p. on 4 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [comments on the amount of work and conditions at the hospital where Marcelle works and her depression; six more ambulances and drivers to arrive; fighting is disheartening, the war tedious and costly; description of the funeral of a young sons-lieutenant, member of a prominent and influential family; anecdote of soldiers and shellfire; witness of the French artillery in action; description of bombardments of the town; jests about how the "doctors that experiment around the Lycee Pasteur" should come to the front; Paul Ayres Rockwell given long leave by the commission; M. Thierrie and the Viscounte de Peloux; constantly at advance point which now serves as their base; description of delightful gardens in the town]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, 1915 May 21; 6 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [pleasure at reading her letters; Paul Ayres Rockwell's difficulties, with his fiancé becoming ill and his brother being wounded; story of the battle at Arras during which Kiffin Yates Rockwell was wounded; [Enos] Curtin's return to America; describes a unique service coming up where two fellows and himself run up into the woods to get the wounded and take them to the different postes de secour; [ ] Rockwell returning to the front in three months; praise of the French]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, 1915 May 31; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [[Enos] Curtin's departure; great deal of fighting; broken records for American Ambulance sections; Marcelle's interest in going to the front as a nurse; continuous bombardments; slightly injured by shrapnel at the most advanced Poste de Secours; comparison of bombardments at posts in a military atmosphere to those in town; description of scene of corpses removed from a store in town]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, [1915 May]; 4 p. on 1 l. (Box Box 1)
      [note sent by Enos Curtin who is on his way to England then to America; moved from base at Dieulouard to Pont-à-Mousson; Ned Salisbury sharing the suite with him; description of the town and the view; trip into Le Bois le Prêtre and through the mutilated Quart en Reserve to the first line trench, where the Germans are only fifty meters distant]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Jun 7; 6 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [Paul Ayres Rockwell and Kiffin Yates Rockwell; Thierry-Delanone being hit in a bombardment; old Russia returning to the fighting; description of the peaceful town of Nancy, including the Place d'Alliance and the gardens; description of his return to the front with an artillery captain, including an observation balloon, various towns, crowds of soldiers, and destroyed buildings; man affected by an asphyxiating shell; sought shelter during a bombardment while writing this letter; evacuation of hospitals in Pont-à-Mousson; an attack in progress at Clas Bois and Montanville; humorous story about an encounter with some "good for nothing doctors" at Ambulance One and his attempt to scare them]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, [1915 Jun 12]; 3 p. on 1 l. (Box Box 1)
      [Barnum and Bailey four ring circus tent anchored near the front; Paul Ayres Rockwell and Kiffin Yates Rockwell]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Jun 15; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [relates that the French do not allow women at the front; hospitals now closed with only one small place to take the severely wounded; description of view from his suite which is shared with Ned Salisbury; Paul Ayres Rockwell's wedding and his desire to see Marcelle at the same time; German attack of their caserne; have twenty field ambulances and a large Hotchkiss and are about to receive the Pierce- Arrow; high regard for the French officer]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Neuilly-sur-Seine, 1915 Jun 18; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [D. D. L. McGraw leaving for the United States; Ned Salisbury taking him on a flying trip to visit the tent squad; ambulance squad to be given the work of an adjacent division as well as the one they are attached to at present]
    - James R. McConnell, Pont-à-Mousson, to Marcelle Guérin, Neuilly-sur- Seine, 1915 Jun 23; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [Paul Ayres Rockwell and his wedding plans; hopes of seeing Marcelle; visit from Captain [ ] Watts, the Australian aviator in the French Army and Lieutenant [ ] Noel, the famous flier; tent squad and firing of several men; fortunate in having the Pierce-Arrow; short on drivers due to three men leaving and difficulty in getting men; to work out of Leincy, Flirey, Fey en Haye, and Auberge St. Pierre; gossip of Nona McAdoo and C. Britton; admiration of Marcelle and her hard work; description of twenty-four hour duty at Dieulouard, where their friends from an Algerian battery in Le Bois le Prêtre gave a concert of Arab songs; sad circumstances surrounding the deaths of the soldiers and the absence of news for their families; encloses postcard of "Bombardement de Pont-à-Mousson"]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Jul 1; 3 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [news of the tent squad and Nona McAdoo prevalent; no wounded yet at the four ring circus; six ambulances detached to handle the second stage of their evacuation work; to remain on the front all the time now, with no trips to the train; Paul Ayres Rockwell and Kiffin Yates Rockwell; arrival of the Pierrce-Arrow]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Jul 8; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [admiration for Marcelle's hard work as a nurse; description of a typical trip with wounded from the front to the Ambulance and the hospital; discourse on the animosity toward the attendants and surgeons who don't seem to care as much about the wounded men; Fourth of July celebration with guests Captain Watt and Lieutenant Noel and German bombardments in the background; evacuations to points below the fighting zone; [Walter] Lovell and [Ned Salisbury]]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Jul 18; 4 p.on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [[ ] Carb and [Paul Ayres] Rockwell; news that Ambulance No. 1 is being sent to the town below and No. 3 brought up; making application for a leave in September to go to Paris; Betty Baldwin leaving for the United States; news of the Russian retreat and future consequences of their newly trained armies in the spring; admiration of the French as the "wonderful, noble, people of this war" and disdain for the British taking credit; the United States' increase in the supply of ammunition]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Jul 21; 2 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [encloses "Lime-Light Lyrics III Marie-Odile or The Nun and the Hun" by Oliver Herford from "Pen and Inklings,"
      Harper's Weekly
      Ned Salisbury to Paris for eight days; stopped in middle of letter to make long evacuation; Paul [Ayres Rockwell] and his wedding plans; concern for Marcelle overworking]
    - James R. McConnell, [Calvados], to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Jul 31; 8 p. on 2 l. w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [no ambulances left in Pont-à-Mousson; reorganization has split up the section so that ten men remain in service on the front and the remainder take care of the work below; Walter Lovell made squad leader; bureau moved to a splendid estate just out of town and nearer their postes de secour; share house with [Ned] Salisbury; description of a Lieutenant Kullman; Waldo Pierce to join them; relates tale of Waldo Pierce and Jack Reed; German who previously lived in the room left some good tobacco; Allies have new shell that is combination asphyxiating and incendiary]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Aug 15; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [plans of Paul [Ayres Rockwell]; Betty Baldwin; Miss Williams leaving the hospital; marvellous mobile ambulance in their secteur; one of twenty-one units in France; comments on her letters becoming formal; death and funeral of a soldier injured when Mignot was killed]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Aug 18; 8 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [discouraged that he may not be able to see her since she has been assigned to the cart and must sleep in the hospital; tent has five patients]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1915 Aug 29]; 2 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [permission for leave around the 15th of September; Frank Page attending sister's wedding in London and is marrying a Miss Sexton from Auburn, New York; Kiffin Yates Rockwell transferred to the aviation service; while at the front their town had a devastating bombardment]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Sep 7; 2 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [finalizing plans for his visit to Paris; disappointment in the disgraceful exhibition shown by the United States towards the war; pride in the actions of France]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Sep 29; 2 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [relates the delightful time they spent together in Paris and Versailles; wishes to be where he can be of more use]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1915 Oct 8]; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [waiting to hear about his application [to aviator school]; Ned Salisbury on a family case in the United States so he and [Walter] Lovell must be in charge; his article in
      The Outlook
      ]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1915] Oct 11; 4 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [plans to visit her in Paris in a month and a half on his way to [aviator] school; will remain on duty until the return of [Ned] Salisbury; detailed description of a French chasseur plane shooting down a German aeroplane and the resulting crash and its aftermath]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Oct 16; 1 p. w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [ill with a cold; [ ] Shroder from Holland nearly hit by shell; another recruit for aeronautic service named [Willis Bradley] Haviland]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Oct 23; 2 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [letter from [Paul Ayres] Rockwell claims that Marcelle looks unhealthy from working too hard; concern over her having a breakdown; [ ] Johnson at Pau is discouraged; Thierry-Delanone working for him; [Walter] Lovell]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Oct 27; 2 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [concern for Marcelle working herself into a bad condition; praises her, writing that it's "your kind that's making for French women the most glorious reputation..."; visit to Paris depends on the return of Ned [Salisbury] and the success of Thierry-Delanone in getting him sent to Avord instead of Pau; another good man, a prize gunner in the Navy, has made application [to aviator school]]
    - James R. McConnell to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, 1915 Nov 13; 3 p. on 2 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [move to Avord; Thierry-Delanone ill with diphtheria so is trying to gain help of General [Joseph Simon] Gallieni; effects of his article in
      , including a visit from Gaudet; arrival of a writer named [Emory] Pottle; estranged from family because of his attitude towards the United States and his refusal to return home during the hard times; plans to visit Paris in early December on his way to Avord or Pau; postponement of Paul [Ayres Rockwell]'s wedding]
    - James R. McConnell, Neuilly-sur-Seine, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1915] Nov 14; 2 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [went with [Walter] Lovell and [Emory] Pottle to the Mairie to meet the President of France, [Raymond] Poincaré; tri-color French flag blowing in the snow reminded him of his and Marcelle's trip to the little islands of St. Pierre and Miguelon]
    - James R. McConnell, Grand Hotel de la Cloche, Dijon, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1915 Dec 28]; 4 p. on 1 l., w/env. (Box Box 1)
      [waiting for train in order to return to Paris and then on to Pau; amusing story of the choice of all sorts of uniforms and what he did choose at the aviation camp]
    - James R. McConnell, Pau, to Marcelle Guérin, Paris, [1916 Jan 5] (Box Box 1)
      [started flight training]